<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two sermons the first preached upon January the 29, 1687/8, upon occasion of Her Majesties happy conception : the second, June the 17th, 1688, upon the birth of the prince / by John Turner ...</title>
            <author>Turner, John, b. 1649 or 50.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63923</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3320</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10476</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11818570</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11818570</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49554</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63923)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49554)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 554:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two sermons the first preached upon January the 29, 1687/8, upon occasion of Her Majesties happy conception : the second, June the 17th, 1688, upon the birth of the prince / by John Turner ...</title>
                  <author>Turner, John, b. 1649 or 50.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Randall Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49554:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49554:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO SERMONS.</p>
            <p>The FIRST preached upon <hi>JANUARY</hi> the 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 1687/8. Upon Occaſion of Her Majeſties HAPPY CONCEPTION. The SECOND, <hi>JUNE</hi> the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 1688. UPON THE BIRTH OF THE PRINCE.</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Turner,</hi> Hoſpitaller of St. <hi>Thomas Southwark.</hi> Licenſed, <hi>June</hi> the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 1688.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Randal Taylor,</hi> near <hi>Statio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners-Hall.</hi> MDCLXXXVIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:49554:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49554:2"/>
            <head>To the KING.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THeſe Diſcourſes which were ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered in Obedience to Your Majeſties Command, and out of a Principle of Zeal and Loyalty to Your Sacred Perſon and Heroic Line, are now humbly proſtrate at Your Royal Feet, as a ſmall, but hearty and ſincere Teſtimony of the Duty and Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of their Author.</p>
            <p>God grant we may have more occaſion for Solemnities of this kind, and that Your Majeſty may live to ſee a numerous Iſſue, that may eſtabliſh and aſſure the Throne, and carry down the Image of Your Princely Virtues to the lateſt Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Times to come,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>May it pleaſe Your moſt Sacred and Serene <hi>Majeſty,</hi> Your Majeſties moſt Humble, Dutiful, and Obedient Subject, and Servant, JOHN TURNER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:49554:3"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THE Second Sermon, as may be ſeen by the Cloſe of the Firſt, and by its own Beginning, was deſigned only to be a Continuation of the Firſt, in which the Miſeries of Anarchy are diſplayed, as in the other, the Bleſſings of Government are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented; but being with very little Alteration and Addition, applicable to the Sacred and Auſpicious Birth upon which it was delivered, inſtead of being preparatory, as it was firſt deſigned, it is now hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly dedicated to the Service and Solemnity of that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Day that gave us ſo delightful, and ſo ſweet a Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of the continuance of thoſe Joys and Bleſſings that are the glorious Theme and Subject of it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>IN the firſt Sermon,</hi> Pag. 30. l. 10. Read <hi>Expreſly. Second Sermon,</hi> p. 2. l. 10. r. <hi>ſo particularly.</hi> p. 5. l. 7. for <hi>and,</hi> r. <hi>as.</hi> l. 8. for <hi>as,</hi> r. <hi>met.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49554:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON, Preached upon <hi>JANUARY</hi> the 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 1688. Upon Occaſion of Her Majeſties HAPPY CONCEPTION.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>JUDG. 17. 6.</bibl>
               <q>In thoſe Days there was no King in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but every Man did that which was right in his own Eyes.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>BEing unhappily prevented by Indiſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, upon the Day appointed for this City and Suburbs, and the Parts ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent, to expreſs their Thankfulneſs to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, for the Hopes he hath given us
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49554:4"/> of aſcertaining the Succeſſion of the Royal Line, and eſtabliſhing the Throne for ever in a regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and peaceable Deſcent, by a new Proſpect of Majeſtic Iſſue, from the Loyns of our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign and his Royal Conſort; I hope I ſhall be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily excuſed, if rather than be wholly wanting in my Duty upon ſo great and ſolemn an Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, I have taken hold of this other Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to offer up my worthleſs, but ſincere Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, at a time when the whole Nation is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaguering Heaven, and laying ſiege to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Goodneſs, for an happy and ſuccesful End of ſuch fair, auſpicious and promiſing Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and the Shout of a King is among them. Beſides, when I conſider how unfit I am to bear any part in ſo glorious a Scene, I ought to chuſe rather to appear in ſuch a numerous Multitude of Votaries, as may at once conceal and drown my Imperfections in a Cloud of Incenſe, and ſupply my Poverty, Infirmity and Weakneſs, by its united and confederate Strength.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore, if you pleaſe, that we may take the truer Eſtimate, and have the more juſt and worthy Apprehenſions of that Extraordinary Bleſſing, which God in his Mercy ſeems to have deſigned us, if our Sins or our Ingratitude do not diſappoint it; begin at
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49554:4"/> the Tragedies of Anarchy and Confuſion, or at that wretched and calamitous Condition of a miſerable People, which reſembles that of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> after the Death of <hi>Sampſon, When there was no King in</hi> Iſrael, <hi>but every Man did that which was right in his own Eyes.</hi> The Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of which, was <hi>Firſt,</hi> the Deſtruction of the National Religion of the Jews, and the crumbling it into numberleſs Parties and Diſtinctions, as appears immediately by the the Story of <hi>Micah,</hi> who conſecrated and ſet a part a proper and peculiar <hi>Levite</hi> for himſelf and Family; in the twelfth and thirteenth Verſes of this Chapter. <hi>And</hi> Micah <hi>conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Levite, and the young Man became his Prieſt, and was in the Houſe of</hi> Micah; <hi>then ſaid</hi> Micah, <hi>now know I that the Lord will do me good, ſeeing I have a Levite to my Prieſt.</hi> And as he had a <hi>Levite,</hi> ſo alſo a Religion peculiar to himſelf, and that Religion was no other than down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Idolatry, under pretence of Purity and Reformation. For in the fourteenth Verſe of the next Chapter, we find mention of his <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phod</hi> and his <hi>Teraphim,</hi> his graven and his molten Image; and this is very certain, by a long Courſe of Experience, that where there is not a common Band of Unity in the Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49554:5"/> there can be much leſs any face of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niformity in Religious Worſhip; but Religion will naturally degenerate for the moſt part, from the Particular Fancies and Inclinations of Men left at random to determine for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, either into Idolatry or Superſtition on the one hand, or into Prophaneneſs and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm on the other; but more eſpecially into the latter of theſe, becauſe where Property is deſtroy'd, as it is in ſuch a State, where there is no King, no Form of Government, no Law-making Wiſdom, no Executing Power, Neceſſity makes every thing become juſt and lawful, and the Judge of that Neceſſity is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Man's private Breaſt; ſo that Rapine puts on an Heroic Shape, and Violence, when ſucceſsful, hath the outward Semblance of a noble Magnanimity and commendable Courage. It is the Law only that firſt deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines Property, and then ſecures it when it is determined; and where there is no Property, there muſt be endleſs Confuſion, by every Man's raking and ſcrambling for himſelf; ſo that every Man, in ſuch a State<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as this, is in apparent danger of immediate Ruine, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing impoſſible that either Strength or Counſel ſhould be of much avail in ſuch a Lawleſs and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49554:5"/> Arbitrary Poſture of Affairs; but of all Men, they that are the moſt expoſed, are <hi>Firſt,</hi> the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm and Helpleſs, <hi>Secondly,</hi> the Raſh and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate, that apprehend the leaſt of any Calamity likely to befall them; and <hi>Thirdly</hi> and laſtly, the Virtuous and Innocent, ſuch as are naturally inclined to Peace, and would fain be upon Terms of mutual Accommodati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and cannot think of continuing ſuch Hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities as theſe, without Regret from within, as well as Terror from without; till at length it comes to paſs that Barbarity and Cruelty, and Treachery and Injuſtice growing epidemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and familiar things, and it ſeeming by that univerſal Miſery and Confuſion, in which Mankind is ſo deſperately involved, as if all things were govern'd by Miſ-rule and by Chance, and as if the Divinity took no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Care of the Peace, Welfare and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of Men, this naturally iſſues in at leaſt an Indifference for neglected Virtue, when it appears to have ſo ſmall a ſhare in the Favor and Patronage of Heaven, that Wickedneſs it ſelf is of the two more ſafe, and it proceeds by very eaſie and intelligible Steps to a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief of God's Providence, and a Contempt of his Attributes, till at laſt it ends, and ſets
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49554:6"/> up its impious and abominable reſt, in a bold and barefac'd denial of his Exiſtence.</p>
            <p>And this is the ſecond Conſequence which I intended to mention, as the neceſſary and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable Event of there being no King in <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> no Supream Judge, no Legiſlative or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutive Power, that by this means Property is deſtroyed, infinite Strife and Contention intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, the Fences of Right and Juſtice broken down, and all Claims are decided by the ſtrongeſt Arm, and by the longeſt Sword. From whence it follows likewiſe, by multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city and frequency of bad Examples that Men are hardened and inured to Miſchief, ſunk in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Atheiſm and Infidelity, and carried head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long by a double Torrent of Precedent and Perſwaſion, uniting and mingling their confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Streams into all manner of Injuſtice, Impiety and Lewdneſs.</p>
            <p>From hence it was that the <hi>Danites,</hi> in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry next Chapter, ſeized upon the <hi>Ephod</hi> and <hi>Tera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phim</hi> the graven Image, and the molten Image of <hi>Micah,</hi> and carried his Prieſt along with them to be a Father and a Prieſt to themſelves, after a moſt unwarrantable and arbitrary manner, there being no King in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> nor any that might controul or contradict their Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49554:6"/> or ſay unto them with Authority, <hi>What do ye?</hi> as <hi>Micah</hi> ſaid to them, but without it, in the eighteenth Verſe of that Chapter, to which they returned no Anſwer but a Menace, and the Cauſe was not decided by Argument but by Power. For the Children of <hi>Dan</hi> ſaid unto him, <hi>Let not thy Voice be heard among us, leſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry Fellows run upon thee, and thou looſe thy Life, with the Lives of thy Houſhold; and when</hi> Micah <hi>ſaw that they were too ſtrong for him, he turned back and went back unto his Houſe.</hi> It is true, that all the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had an expreſs Commiſſion to cut down the Groves of Heathens and Idolaters, to overthrow their Altars, and burn their graven Images with Fire, as often as they had Power and Opportunity to do it; but this was not the Caſe of the <hi>Danites</hi> at this time, who were as very Idolaters as the other, only they altered the Property from <hi>Micah</hi> to themſelves, ſo that they were guilty of Robbery, Idolatry and Sacriledge together; the Robbery con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted in the violent Detention of what was not their own, the Idolatry, in worſhiping the Images they had ſtollen, and the Sacriledge, in ſtealing what they account Sacred, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faning what they worſhipped, by Rapine and Injuſtice. And not unlike to this it is,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49554:7"/> what we find in the ſeventh Verſe of that Chapter, concerning the Men of <hi>Laiſh,</hi> to whom the five Men of the <hi>Danites</hi> were ſent as Spies: <hi>The five Men departed,</hi> ſaith the Text, <hi>and came to</hi> Laiſh, <hi>and ſaw the People that were therein, how they dwelt careleſs, after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the</hi> Zidonians, <hi>quiet, and ſecure, and there was no Magiſtrate in the Land that might put them to ſhame in any thing, and they were far from the</hi> Zido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, <hi>and had no buſineſs with any Man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Now this <hi>Laiſh</hi> was otherwiſe called <hi>Leſhem,</hi> as it is in the <hi>19th.</hi> of <hi>Joſhua</hi> at the <hi>7th.</hi> Verſe, and was a Colony of the <hi>Zidonians,</hi> as appears very probable from this Place, and from the <hi>28th.</hi> Verſe of this Chapter, where, when the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi> made their Aſſault upon it; it is ſaid, <hi>There was no Deliverer, becauſe they were far from Zidon,</hi> their Confederate City, from whence they were at firſt deſcended, and had not only brought along with them the ill Manners of that Place, which was to a Proverb infamous for all ſorts of Luxury and Vice, but there being no Law to regulate their Exorbitances, or to chaſtiſe and puniſh notorious Offenders, mutual Conſent added to reciprocal Example, where there was no Magiſtrate in the Land that might put them to Shame, and bring
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49554:7"/> them to condign Puniſhment for their Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſoon fill'd up the Meaſure of their crying Sins, and made them ripe for the Judgment that overtook them, Their City<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> being burnt, and themſelves ſmitten by the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi> with the Edge of the Sword.</p>
            <p>If by reaſon of their Impunity, and Want of Government, which is the Cauſe of all Miſchief and Diſorder in a Nation, they did not yet, notwithſtanding, fall out among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; this is to be imputed to the ſmallneſs of their Number, for they were conquered by no<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> more than ſix hundred Men, compared with the ſtrange Plenty and Exuberance of their Soil, a Place <hi>where there was no Want of any thing that is on the Earth,</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently with a very ſmall degree of Husban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry and Tillage, it was capable of afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them a plentiful Subſiſtance, without the Temptation of preying upon each other; To which we muſt refer likewiſe what the Text ſaith farther of them, <hi>That they were far from the</hi> Zidonians, <hi>and had no buſineſs with any Man:</hi> That is, they had no need of Traffic and Commerce, but gave themſelves up whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to Pleaſure and Enjoyment, having ſo bountiful and rich a Soil to furniſh them at
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49554:8"/> Home with whatever they deſired, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>they were far from the Zidonians,</hi> not only in reſpect of Diſtance or of Place, but in this alſo, that they were not a Bartering and a Trading People, as the <hi>Zidonians</hi> were, who were the greateſt Merchants of thoſe Days, and as they encreaſed in Wealth, ſo alſo in Luxury and Intemperance likewiſe; they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported the Vices<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of foreign Nations together with their Commodities, and united the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieties of ſeveral Climates in one, and were known to be Merchants, not only by their Ships, and by their Wares, but by their Sins. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> When it is ſaid, as well of the Men of <hi>Laiſh,</hi> as of <hi>Zidon, That they were a are leſs, a Quiet, and a ſecure People;</hi> this is alſo to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed to the Plenty of both Places, to the Natural Plenty of the one, and beſides the Natural, to the Artificial Plenty of the other. For Plenty and Eaſe, do naturally ſoften and debaſe Men's Minds into a wanton Spirit of Effeminacy and Luſt, into a Liſtleſs Habit of Idleneſs and Sloth, into a Fools Paradiſe of Security and Reſt; though in the midſt of, Dangers round about them, and the Fumes of Wine that can raiſe Apparitions of Imaginary Dangers, have uſually no Senſe of thoſe that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49554:8"/> are certain and real. But this was by no means equally the Caſe of the <hi>Zidonians,</hi> and the Men of <hi>Laiſh;</hi> for the firſt were not only ſecure by Luxury and Intemperance, a ſort of Security to which it is very ill truſting, but they had a fortified City, a formidable fleet, a numerous People, and a ſpacious Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and could upon any Occaſion furniſh out an Army, that ſhould be much ſuperior to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their Neighbours, and were, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Vices they were guilty of, ty'd together by an Eſtabliſhment comparatively firm, under the Command of Magiſtrates, and the Obligation of Laws, ſo that they had rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be ſecure and at reſt, conſidering how eaſily they ſate at Home, and how ſafe they were from any Apprehenſion Abroad.</p>
            <p>But with the Men of <hi>Laiſh</hi> it was clean o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, they had no Magiſtrate, no Judge of Controverſies, no Reconciler of Differences, no Avenger of Injuſtice, no Puniſher of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences; and beſides this, they were but few in Number, they were ſituate in a Mid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>land<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Country, and had no Advantage of Traffic and Commerce abroad, which begets Leagues and Dependencies among Men, that may be rely'd upon in a dangerous Time, they
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49554:9"/> were forſaken and forgotten by their very Country-men the <hi>Zidonians</hi> themſelves, and encompaſſed all about by Enemies and Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, ſo that their Security was indeed but a lethargick Stupour, which was owing either to Intemperance and Fulneſs, or elſe to a vain Perſwaſion which they ſeem to have had, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their Neighbours for a long time never had attempted them, that they never would; but the Text inclines rather to the <hi>Zidonian</hi> Evil, whoſe Eaſe and Security was in part ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Steams of Gluttony, the Exceſs of Wine, and the Supinity of Dalliance and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment; and though the Text mentions no other Effect of that Anarchy that was to be found at that time among the Lawleſs Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of <hi>Laiſh,</hi> but only <hi>that they were careleſs, and quiet, and ſecure, and having no Magiſtrate to put them to any Shame,</hi> were grown to a ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs paſs of Luxury and Lewdneſs, yet upon ſuppoſition that they did not fall out and quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel among themſelves, which is no more than a natural Effect of Anarchy and Miſ-rule, where all Men are Lords and Sovereigns by themſelves, and every one diſdains the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a Servant, and ſpurns at the very Thoughts of Obedience and Subjection; yet
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49554:9"/> to be ſunk into Concupiſcence, and immerſt in Luſt, to have no ſenſe of Conſcience, of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, or of Shame, and to be given up whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the miſerable Conduct of brutal Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites, and beaſtly Inclinations, are things, to wiſe and good Men, that ſhall ſeriouſly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them, more loathſome than Stench and Putrefaction themſelves, more intolerable than the moſt exquiſite and ingenious Torments, more dreadful than the moſt lingring, or the moſt ſhameful Death; they dethrone our Reaſon, they debaſe our Underſtandings, and rob us of thoſe true and limpid Pleaſures which ariſe only from Wiſdom and from Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, they imply an Anarchy in every private Breaſt, or which is ſtill worſe, if any thing can be worſe, they conſtitute ſuch a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment within our Souls, as when a Prince is governed by his Slaves, and they too Falling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out and Claſhing with one another, by the Competition of Paſſions among themſelves, and are a living and a ſtanding Infamy and Reproach to the nobleſt Faculties belonging to Humane Nature.</p>
            <p>But if we reflect attentively upon the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Conſequence of Gluttonny and Intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, which in the Experience of all Times
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49554:10"/> and Places, is big with Animoſity in a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Shapes, and with a numberleſs Variety of Miſchief and Diſorder, and if to this we add the fewneſs of their Number, being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered, and all of them ſmitten with the Edge of the Sword, by a ſmall Party of ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Men; it will be highly probable, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witſtanding that Quiet and Security they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed; by which the Text means no more, than that they had no Apprehenſion of any Diſturbance or Danger from abroad; that yet at Home, in the midſt of ſo many, and ſo great Enormities, without any Magiſtrate to puniſh, or any Law to reſtrain them, they were ſeldom or never free from ſome Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtic and Inteſtine Broil, in which, though the whole Nation were not at a time engaged, yet it is enough if private Perſons, by the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valſhip of Love, or by the Surpriſe of unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected Feuds, occaſioned by Wine or Luſt, or by the Ambition of Men, that in a lawleſs E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, would every one endeavor to be great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than his Neighbour, did perpetually<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> from ſuch Cauſes and Accidents as theſe, deſtroy and ruine one another, and by new Grudges, everlaſtingly ſpringing and ſpawning from the old, hinder the Encreaſe and Propagation of their People.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:49554:10"/>
            <p>For it is highly reaſonable to believe, that this Nation or Colony of <hi>Zidonian</hi> Planters, were actually ſeated where the <hi>Danites</hi> found them, even before the coming of <hi>Moſes</hi> out of <hi>Aegypt;</hi> and it is certain that <hi>Joſhua</hi> found them there when he made the Partition of Inneri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances to the Tribes, at which time, this very Place was conquer'd by the Tribe of <hi>Dan;</hi> but it ſeems, though the Inhabitants were bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and as many as could not ſecure themſelves by Flight, or by Conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, were ſmitten with the Sword, yet they were ſo far from being utterly deſtroyed, that afterwards they made Head again againſt their Enemies, and made them quit their new Conqueſt to the old Poſſeſſors, who enjoy'd it for ſome Ages afterwards, without Trouble or Moleſtation, and had now leſs reaſon to be afraid than ever, conſidering what it was not eaſie for them to be wholly ignorant of, that there was now no King in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and that they had been formerly too hard for thoſe who were how a diſ-united and diſ joynted People, at a Time when their Strength was unanimous and compact, which was without queſtion one reaſon of the Quiet and Security which they now enjoy'd, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49554:11"/> they were ſo ſmall and inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a People.</p>
            <p>For to ſay that they were a numerous and a Powerful Nation, and yet that they were deſtroyed and utterly cut off by a poor Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of ſix hundred Men, is to affirm they were deſtroy'd by Miracle, as the <hi>Amorites,</hi> and the <hi>Perizzites</hi> and other Nations were at the firſt entrance of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> into the Land of <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an;</hi> but this being only a ſupernatural Effect of the Divine Vengeance and Diſpleaſure, for the Inceſt, Idolatry, Beaſtiality and other horrid Crimes of thoſe accurſed Wretches, whom God had utterly devoted to Deſtruction, and reſolved to give their Land for an Inheritance to his choſen People; this reaſon will not hold with the <hi>Danites</hi> at this time, who were as ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Idolaters as thoſe whom they deſtroyed, and therefore it is very unjuſt and unreaſonable to expect in ſuch a Caſe and Circumſtance as this, that any miraculous Aids ſhould be afforded them. Neither is it any more to the purpoſe, that they asked Counſel of the Prieſt of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cah,</hi> to know whether God would proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per their Undertaking, <hi>and the Prieſt ſaid unto them, go in peace before, the Lord is the Way wherein ye go.</hi> So that they ſeem to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49554:11"/> have acted by a Divine Commiſſion; for it is to be conſidered that this Prieſt of his was but a <hi>Puiſne</hi> Prieſt, or rather indeed he was no Prieſt at all, ſo far as that Office is of a Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Nature, for he was not of the Sons of <hi>Aaron,</hi> but only a <hi>Common Levite,</hi> and he was conſecrated to the Prieſthood by <hi>Micah,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Expreſs Inſtitution of the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> as he likewiſe conſecrated one of his own Sons in the fifth Verſe of that Chapter, but had no Right or Authority to do either. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> It is plain by the Text, that he was an Idolater, and therefore had no reaſon to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect any ſuch extraordinary<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Aſſiſtances from Above, as ſhould acquaint him with the ſecret Deſigns of God's Providence, in the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration and Government of the World. <hi>Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> The only way of oracular Reſponſes to be met with among the <hi>Jews,</hi> was by the <hi>Urim</hi> and <hi>Thummim,</hi> which was peculiar to the <hi>High Prieſt</hi> alone, and never in any one Inſtance communicated or vouchſafed to any other but him. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> He might conſider the ſeeming Fairneſs and Juſtice of their Cauſe, they going only to retreive their own, and to recover again into their own Poſſeſſion, what their Anceſtors had formerly enjoyed. <hi>Fifth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:49554:12"/> and laſtly, It may very well be ſuppoſed that he was afraid to give a diſſatisfactory An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to ſo many armed Men, leſt they ſhould ſay to him as <hi>Agamemnon</hi> did to <hi>Chalcas</hi> in <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <p>or as <hi>Ahab</hi> did concerning the Prophet <hi>Micajah, I hate him, for he doth not propheſie Good concerning me, but Evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that I think upon the whole Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, it is abundantly manifeſt, that the Strength of the Men of <hi>Laiſh</hi> being very much weakned and impaired by Civil Broils, for want of good Laws to ſettle the Bounds and Meaſures of Obligation, and Magiſtrates to puniſh the Refractory and Diſobedient, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever preſent Accommodation there might be patched up among them, by mutual dread of one another, and mutual Experience of ſo many Ills, as Lawleſs and Arbitrary Courſes had occaſioned, and whatever Eaſe and Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity they might promiſe themſelves from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, not having heard of any Enemy for ſo long a time, yet they became an eaſie Prey from both of theſe Cauſes together, to this unexpected and ſurpriſing Party of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Dan.</hi> To all which, it is ſtill farther
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49554:12"/> to be added, that a diſſolute and licentious People, ſeaſon'd and habituated in exorbitant Courſes, though they may in time be ſenſible of the great and public Detriment that accrues from them, and be perſwaded, by that means, to think of a Regulation for the Redreſs of ſuch grievous Mischiefs and Abuſes; yet they ſcarce know how to give Obedience to thoſe Laws, which they are convinced to be ſo neceſſary for them, but find a certain awkwardneſs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aptneſs in themſelves to be confin'd within any compaſs of Duty, like untaught Heifers, that never felt the Yoak, or Colts that never yet were back'd, or Horſes not ſufficiently inured to their Paces or their Harneſs. And as it would be very difficult in this Caſe, and for a while impracticable to reduce the People into ſuch a State of Obedience as is neceſſary to the Peace and Security of every Common-wealth, ſo it would be much more ſo, to find a fit Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor to preſide over them, becauſe Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment requires a ſteady Reſolution, and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummate Wiſdom, neither of which are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to Obedience, only the Subject is in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral to underſtand: <hi>Firſt,</hi> the Wholſomeneſs of Obedience, for the Conſervation of Peace, and for the uniting a Nation in one common
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49554:13"/> Band againſt all foreign Oppoſers. And <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> The Duty that is incumbent upon him, upon account of both of theſe Conſiderations, to reſign up himſelf chearfully to the Supream Power, for the Common Good of himſelf and of his Country. Government requires a Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage that is not to be daunted by every ſturdy Pretender to Liberty of Action, nor every bold Cenſurer of the Conduct of Affairs, and the Adminiſtration of his Betters at the Helm, let his Pretences be as ſpecious as they will, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires a Wiſdom that looks far backwards in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the good and bad Succeſſes of paſt Times, and into the Reaſons upon which they ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally depended, a Wiſdom that looks forward, and pries with Warineſs and deep Deliberation, into the natural Iſſues and Reſults of Things; and a Wiſdom that is conſummate by Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, in the Management of Affairs, by which a Facility and Dexterity of Action and of Counſel is acquired, as well as by reflection upon the Occurrences of former Times, and Speculation into Humane Nature; without which, no Governour can ſufficiently diſcharge himſelf of the great Truſt that is repoſed in him.</p>
            <p>Now in this Caſe of a diſſolute and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken People, whoſe Necks of a long time had
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49554:13"/> no felt the Yoak, as it would require much greater Wiſdom and Experience to pilot and conduct a ſhattered Veſſel through Paſſions and Prejudices not eaſily to be conquered or charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into Obedience, and which like Rocks and Shelves, not taken notice of by any Sea-chart, like moving Sands, without any Buoys to diſcover them, would every moment endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger the Ship-wrack of the State, than to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern an eſtabliſh'd and orderly Society, that hath been inured to Laws, and ſenſible of the great Advantages accruing by them; ſo it would be much harder to find a Perſon fit for ſuch a weighty Charge in a Government that needs it moſt, then in a ſetled and well regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted State, where half thoſe Abilities would ſerve the turn. Beſides that, the Competiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Pretenders to the Supream Power, and the ſeveral Factions aiding and abetting ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the one or the other, would create new Strife, inſtead of compoſing the old, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all, a wiſe Man, though unanimouſly cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, would ſcarce accept ſo dangerous a Charge, wherein he would be more likely to make himſelf a Victim to the variable Humors of a giddy Multitude, impatient of Subjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and unaccuſtomed to Reſtraint, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49554:14"/> to be controuled and check'd by him that was ſo lately their Equal, than to preſerve his Country, by his Wiſdom and Courage, from its impending Ruine and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation. No wonder therefore, if the Men of <hi>Laiſh,</hi> being without any Government or Laws, and being probably at variance among themſelves, and being ſurpriſed of a ſuddain by an unexpected Aſſault, and their Security adding new Horror to the Surpriſe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing in ſo great a Proportion to their Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, they were for all and every of theſe Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, an eaſie Prey to the Fury of their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and fell a tame Sacrifice to the Revenge of the <hi>Danites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But without reaſoning ſo nicely upon an imperfect account, wherein ſo much is of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity to be ſupplied by conjecture, the next Chapter will afford us a more expreſs Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the horrid Calamities to which Anar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy is Expoſed, for there we have firſt the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Levite and his Concubine, or rather Wife, for ſhe is accuſed of being falſe to his Bed. <hi>And his Concubine,</hi> ſaith the Text, <hi>play'd the Whore againſt him, and went away from him unto her Fathers Houſe to</hi> Bethlehem Judah, <hi>and was there four whole Months.</hi> Now Adultery was
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49554:14"/> Death in both Parties, by the Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> nay, the Guilt of this horrid Crime was under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood to lye at the Door of the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and was threatned to be avenged upon the People themſelves, if they did not expiate it by the Death of the Offenders. Deut. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 22. <hi>If a Man be found lying with a Woman, married to an Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, then they ſhall both of them die, both the Man that lay with the Woman, and the Woman, ſo ſhalt thou put away Evil from</hi> Iſrael. And this was ſtill a more criminal ſort of Adultery, becauſe it was a Levites Wife, a Perſon dedicated and ſet apart to the Service of God, and to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of that Temple in which he had placed his Name, and whether all the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were to repair for Sacrifice and Worſhip. It was much the more hainous Offence in both of the Delinquent Parties upon this account, and therefore the Obligation to puniſh it was ſo much the ſtronger, but this not being to be done without a formal Proceſs, in which the Criminals were to be firſt convict, and then adjudged to undergo the legal Sentence in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of that nature, at a time when there was no Judge in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> no Supreme, nor by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence any ſubordinate Magiſtrate to hear and determine Cauſes, there could be no Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49554:15"/> no Sentence, no Execution. And ſo it came to paſs, not long after, either, by a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of Affection on the Husbands Part, or by ſome advantagious Overtures of Reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on that of the Wife and her Relations, that the Buſineſs, as foul as it was, was made up, and they aſſociated together again; but this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued but for a very little while, when leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Bethlehem Judah,</hi> where the Father of the Woman dwelt, and going homewards through <hi>Gibeah</hi> of <hi>Benjamin,</hi> and lodging there in the Houſe of an hoſpitable <hi>Ephraimite,</hi> the <hi>Man</hi> was firſt demanded by the lewd and lawleſs In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the Place, to be uſed as the <hi>Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites</hi> would have ſerved the Gueſts of <hi>Lot,</hi> and at laſt, the leaſt thing that would appeaſe their Belluine and Brutal Luſt, was the abuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Wife to ſuch a degree, that ſhe died up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Place, and being divided by her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band into twelve Pieces, which were ſent ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally to ſo many ſeveral Tribes, to be an horrid Spectacle and Monument of what had happened, and to incite them the more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to a juſt Revenge of ſo flagitious and vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanous an Action upon the execrable Authors of it, this occaſioned that dreadful Civil War which followed betwixt the Tribe of <hi>Benjamin</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:49554:15"/> and the reſt of the Tribes, who being under no legal Tye of Obligation to one another, and being now deſtitute of a common Head that might command and influence them all, yet met together by common Conſent at <hi>Mizpeh,</hi> and from thence demanded ſatisfaction of the <hi>Benjamites,</hi> for the horrid Wickedneſs commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the <hi>Gibeathites</hi> their Brethren, and for the Scandal that was brought by it, upon the Name and Nation of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which nothing could wipe off, but the Death of thoſe Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creants that were guilty of it; but the <hi>Benja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites</hi> were ſo far from delivering up their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to be puniſh'd as they deſerv'd, that they appeared in their Defence, and were reſolved, as bad as they were, to ſtand up in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of their Lives, with the Hazard of their own, upon which, immediately enſued that bloody War, in which forty thouſand of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and of the <hi>Benjamites,</hi> the whole Tribe, without ſparing either Age or Sex, bate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only ſix hundred, were deſtroyed; nay, their very Cattle and their Cities were not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted, but a deadly Infection ran through all they poſſeſt, and overwhelm'd every thing in the common Ruine. So that in this one Story, though we go no farther, we have a promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49554:16"/> Luſt, a brutal Concupiſcence, and a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive War, Crimes not to be named with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out confuſion and bluſhing, and Judgments not to be mentioned without trembling, and all for want of a Judge and a King in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> whoſe Authority might prevent the Perpetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch Villany, or at leaſtwiſe puniſh the beginnings of it, before it proceeded to ſuch a bloody Conſequence, and tragical Concluſion.</p>
            <p>But this is not all neither, for if I am not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much miſtaken, there was a Famine likewiſe happened upon this occaſion, for in the Book of <hi>Ruth</hi> we read that <hi>in the Days when the Judges rul'd, there was a Famine in the Land,</hi> upon which <hi>Elimelech</hi> and his Wife <hi>Naomi,</hi> and his two Sons <hi>Mahlon</hi> and <hi>Chilion</hi> went and ſojourned in the Country of <hi>Moab,</hi> where <hi>Elimelech</hi> and his two Sons died, and <hi>Naomi,</hi> after having dwelt there ten years, <hi>aroſe with her Daughters in Law, that ſhe might return from the Country of</hi> Moab, <hi>for ſhe had heard in the Country of</hi> Moab, <hi>how that the Lord had viſited his People in giving them Bread.</hi> Now though it be ſaid that this happened in the Days when the Judges rul'd, all that is meant by it is no more than this, that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired Writer who wrote this Book, wrote it a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49554:16"/> time afterwards, in the time of the Kings, and by the <hi>Days of the Judges,</hi> or <hi>when the Judges rull'd,</hi> all that Period or Interval of time is underſtood, which paſſed between <hi>Joſhua,</hi> or rather between <hi>Moſes</hi> the firſt Judge, and <hi>Saul</hi> the firſt King of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and the Age of <hi>Ruth</hi> falls juſt upon the Cloſe of this Account, for her Son was <hi>Obed,</hi> who was the Father of <hi>Jeſſe,</hi> the Father of <hi>David;</hi> ſo that the Times of <hi>Obed</hi> and <hi>Jeſſe</hi> muſt be coincident with thoſe of <hi>Eli</hi> and <hi>Samuel,</hi> the laſt Judges of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the beginning of the Reign of <hi>Saul,</hi> the firſt King; and ſince we have no mention of any Judge of <hi>Iſrael</hi> after <hi>Sampſon,</hi> before <hi>Eli,</hi> it muſt needs appear very likely, that this Famine hapned after the Death of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> when there was no King or Judge in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when the want of Laws made Induſtry to ceaſe, and Husbandry to fall to Ruine and Decay, and when the Animoſities and Contentions that hapned in thoſe days, were a Diſcouragement to the Husband-man from ſetting his Hand to the Plow, or ſcattering the Seeds upon the Earth in their Seaſon, when he had ſo little ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity that he ſhould reap the Encreaſe. And otherwiſe than this it will ſeem utterly impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, without a perpetual Miracle all that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49554:17"/> while, that in <hi>Moab,</hi> a neighbouring Country, there ſhould be ſo great Plenty for ten years together, and yet ſo great Scarcity in the Land of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> that flowed with Milk and Honey, and was naturally ſo rich and plentiful a Spot of Ground, for it is not without a miraculous Interpoſition of Divine Providence, that Countries naturally fruitful, and being of the ſame Soil and Climate, and very nearly bordering upon each other, ſhould the one be afflicted with a ten years Famine, while the other, all that while, was not only able to ſuſtain it ſelf, but to ſupply the Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of its Neighbours, and we are certainly informed, that when the ſeaven years Famine was in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> there was the ſame Scarcity in the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and other neighbouring Countries in that Part of the World, only the Wiſdom and prophetic Fore-ſight of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> who was then the chief Miniſter in <hi>Pharaoh's</hi> Court, had made a better Proviſion by Good-huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry, in the Time of Plenty, for the Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> than any of the neighbour Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions had made for themſelves; ſo that it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears very reaſonable to think, that a Famine was one of thoſe diſmal Conſequences that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended the Anarchy or want of Government a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49554:17"/> the <hi>Jews,</hi> after the Death of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> and the Expreſſion of <hi>Naomi</hi> is remarkable, <hi>That the Lord had viſited his People in giving them Bread;</hi> he viſited them by giving them Bread, and he gave them Bread by viſiting them, that is, by ſetting a Viſitor or Inſpector over them, a Judge that might retrench the Exorbitances, and redreſs the Abuſes under which they groan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for as <hi>Phacad</hi> in Hebrew ſignifies to <hi>viſit,</hi> ſo does <hi>Phakid,</hi> derived from it, ſignifie a <hi>Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> or Inſpector, a Governour, a Judge, a King, or any one that is inveſted with a Legiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative and Coercive Power, and as Mercy and Juſtice do equally belong to the Notion and Character of ſuch a Perſon, ſo God himſelf, who is the great Sovereign and Potentate of the World, as well when he inflicts his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as beſtows his Mercy, is ſaid to viſit Mankind.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude theſe Obſervations upon the Text and Context, with obſerving how care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful the inſpired Pen man of this Book of <hi>Judges</hi> is, to let us know that all theſe Enormities and Calamities which he recounts, were the Effects and Iſſues of there being no King in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> though indeed he does not ſay ſo in ſo many Words, but he does as plainly imply it as any
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49554:18"/> thing can be. For when he tells us the Story of <hi>Micah,</hi> and his <hi>Ephod</hi> and Prieſt, he tells us alſo at the ſame time, <hi>In thoſe days there was no King in</hi> Iſrael, <hi>but every Man did that which was right in his own Eyes.</hi> And the ſame Words are again repeated in the next Chapter, where the <hi>Danites</hi> of their own Heads, without any Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or Commiſſion, to that purpoſe, make War upon the Men of <hi>Laiſh,</hi> and of the eaſie Conqueſt they obtained the reaſon is expreſs aſſigned, becauſe the Men of <hi>Laiſh dwelt care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, after the manner of the</hi> Zidonians, <hi>and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there was no Magiſtrate in the Land that might put them to ſhame in any thing;</hi> ſo that they were a looſe and a divided People; and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately before the Story of the Levite and his Concubine, which drew ſuch diſmal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences after it, it is again inculcated and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated, <hi>And it came to paſs in thoſe days, when there was no King</hi> Iſrael, <hi>that there was a certain Levite,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>Laſtly,</hi> In the Concluſion of the whole Book, where the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> after the War with <hi>Benjamin,</hi> disband and fall in pieces again, going every Man to his own Tent, and after his own Imagination, he ends as he began, with the ſame remarkable Words, <hi>In thoſe days there was no King in</hi> Iſrael,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49554:18"/> 
               <hi>every Man did that which was right in his own Eyes;</hi> and then in probability that Famine followed which I have now newly deſcribed.</p>
            <p>But it is in vain to purſue this Argument any farther, the Miſeries of Anarchy are ſo many and ſo great, that there is no Tongue ſufficient to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs them, nor any Conception large enough to comprehend them; they are as variable as the Paſſions and Deſigns of Men, or the Occaſions upon which they happen, and as Bloody, as Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, Ambition, Injuſtice and Revenge can make them; and if the Reins of Diſcipline were let looſe upon our Necks, or the Bridle of Obedience perfectly taken off, and every Man let alone to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in his own Senſe, and purſue his own Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations as far as he thought fit, it would ſoon come to paſs that the World, by the interfering Paſſions, and incompoſſible Deſires and Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites of unreaſonable Men, would be turned into a Wilderneſs of Thorns and Briars, a Den of Thieves, a Foreſt of wild Beaſts, a <hi>Chaos</hi> of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, a miſerable Spectacle of Deſtruction and of Death diſplaying and brandiſhing its frightful Terrors in a thouſand ſeveral ghaſtly and lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Forms, a Theatre fill'd with deſperate Gladia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, perpetually goring and ſtabbing one another, a Slaughter-houſe for Innocence, an inextricable Snare for Weakneſs, a Temple, but not a Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49554:19"/> for Oppreſſion, a Region of Devils in the Shape of Men; ſo that the old War betwixt the Giants and the Gods, which the Poets have repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, as much the moſt terrible and outragious thing that even Fancy and Fable would ſtretch themſelves to conceive, would of a ſuddain ceaſe to be Romantic any longer, and inſtead of being Fabulous, as it now appears, it would paſs for a cold and an imperfect Truth, not worthy the Name of a Poetical Contrivance, nor fit to be compared with the real Animoſities that would intoxicate and embroil Mankind. It is but fit therefore in the midſt of ſuch horrid and diſmal Apparitions, as the Conſideration of Anarchy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents us with, before we enter upon the bleſſed and the glorious Scene of Eſtabliſhment and Order, to let down ſoftly the Curtain of Confuſion, that our Thoughts may be compoſed and quiet, as the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene, beautiful and peaceful Subject about which they are to be employ'd, and that we may reliſh the better the Happineſs of Government, and pray the more heartily for the Continuance of it, and for the Birth of a Prince, that may render Empire in an everlaſting Succeſſion, Hereditary to himſelf and his Deſcendents, and entail Peace, Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Charity and Plenty upon all the Subjects of this Imperial Crown, as long as the Sun continues to be conſtant, or the Moon to change.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:49554:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
